<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!--<!DOCTYPE metadata SYSTEM "http://www.esri.com/metadata/esriprof80.dtd">-->
<metadata xml:lang="en"><Esri><CreaDate>20060714</CreaDate><CreaTime>08281300</CreaTime><SyncOnce>FALSE</SyncOnce><SyncDate>20060601</SyncDate><SyncTime>11251200</SyncTime><ModDate>20060714</ModDate><ModTime>08300500</ModTime><MetaID>{55CA491A-7FD2-4F7C-83EB-E7D7B7FE4C76}</MetaID></Esri><idinfo><native Sync="TRUE">Microsoft Windows XP Version 5.1 (Build 2600) Service Pack 2; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.0.0.535</native><descript><langdata Sync="TRUE">en</langdata><abstract>In the spring of 2005, Sanborn as part of the Dewberry team was contracted to execute a LiDAR (Light Detection and Ranging) survey campaign to collect the 3-dimensional positions of a dense set of masspoints for the entire 689 plus square mile project area of Baltimore County, Maryland as defined by the County Boundary and tile boundarys furnished by Baltimore County.  These data are suitable for the development of a digital elevation model (DEM) to support orthometric photo rectification and contouring. Lidar Bare Earth (BE) value data is obtained from the  Last return data and is provided in an ASCII comma delimited format.  The Bare Earth data is delivered in the county furnished standard 4000' by 6000' tile layout.</abstract><purpose>The Baltimore County LiDAR campaign was designed specifically to collect LiDAR derived masspoints at an approximate spacing of 1.5 meters or better within the project area.  The data was processed to facilitate the generation of an appropriate DEM for orthorectification and 2' contour  mapping.  Rigorous quality assurance procedures were followed to ensure that the appropriate data accuracy was achieved.   The BE values have easting and northing in Mayland State Plane coordinates for surface location correlation and elevations in feet.</purpose><supplinf>The original LiDAR Acquisition plan was designed for all E_W flight lines. Due to several Air Traffic Control Restrictions in the southern portion of the County, 54 N_S flight lines were used to acquire the southern portion of the county minimizing time in restricted airspace.  In addition the Bay Coast line area was planned for acquisition within one hour either side of lowtide. Due to the same ATC restrictions it was impossible to comply with the low tide requirement for this area.
The image tile format is provided in the County 4,000' by 6000' tile layout and numbered according to that layout. File naming convention  is 087B1_BE.xyz</supplinf></descript><citation><citeinfo><origin>Dewberry</origin><pubdate>Unknown</pubdate><title Sync="TRUE">BareEarth</title><ftname Sync="TRUE">BareEarth</ftname><geoform Sync="TRUE">vector digital data</geoform><onlink Sync="TRUE">\\BA204074\C$\New Personal Geodatabase.mdb</onlink></citeinfo></citation><timeperd><current>ground condition</current><timeinfo><mdattim><sngdate><caldate> April 2005</caldate></sngdate></mdattim></timeinfo></timeperd><status><progress>Complete</progress><update>None planned</update></status><spdom><bounding><westbc>-76.9156</westbc><eastbc>-76.3155</eastbc><northbc>39.7221</northbc><southbc>39.1934</southbc></bounding><lboundng><leftbc Sync="TRUE">1366000.000000</leftbc><rightbc Sync="TRUE">1372000.000000</rightbc><bottombc Sync="TRUE">586400.000000</bottombc><topbc Sync="TRUE">590600.000000</topbc></lboundng></spdom><keywords><theme><themekey>Baltimore County</themekey><themekey>DEM</themekey><themekey> Digital Elevation Model</themekey><themekey>Elevation</themekey><themekey>Digital Terrain Model</themekey><themekey>Point cloud data</themekey></theme></keywords><accconst>To be filled in by Baltimore County</accconst><useconst>The BE files are considered the primary product produced from Lidar data and is used to perform terrain analysis, generating grids and for contouring.  The BE data has not been enhanced  with breaklines or stereo compiled elevations.</useconst><natvform Sync="TRUE">Personal GeoDatabase Feature Class</natvform><ptcontac><cntinfo><cntaddr><addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype><address>400 Washington Ave</address><city>Towson</city><state>Maryland</state><postal>21204</postal><country>US</country></cntaddr><cntvoice>410-887-2233</cntvoice><cntorgp><cntorg>Baltimore County GIS Services</cntorg></cntorgp><cntemail>gis@co.ba.md.us</cntemail></cntinfo></ptcontac></idinfo><dataIdInfo><envirDesc Sync="TRUE">Microsoft Windows XP Version 5.1 (Build 2600) Service Pack 2; ESRI ArcCatalog 9.0.0.535</envirDesc><dataLang><languageCode Sync="TRUE" value="en"></languageCode></dataLang><idCitation><resTitle Sync="TRUE">BareEarth</resTitle><presForm><PresFormCd Sync="TRUE" value="005"></PresFormCd></presForm></idCitation><spatRpType><SpatRepTypCd Sync="TRUE" value="001"></SpatRepTypCd></spatRpType><dataExt><geoEle><GeoBndBox esriExtentType="native"><westBL Sync="TRUE">1366000</westBL><eastBL Sync="TRUE">1372000</eastBL><northBL Sync="TRUE">590600</northBL><southBL Sync="TRUE">586400</southBL><exTypeCode Sync="TRUE">1</exTypeCode></GeoBndBox></geoEle></dataExt></dataIdInfo><metainfo><langmeta Sync="TRUE">en</langmeta><metstdn Sync="TRUE">FGDC Content Standards for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn><metstdv Sync="TRUE">FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv><mettc Sync="TRUE">local time</mettc><metc><cntinfo><cntorgp><cntper>REQUIRED: The person responsible for the metadata information.</cntper><cntorg>REQUIRED: The organization responsible for the metadata information.</cntorg></cntorgp><cntaddr><addrtype>REQUIRED: The mailing and/or physical address for the organization or individual.</addrtype><city>REQUIRED: The city of the address.</city><state>REQUIRED: The state or province of the address.</state><postal>REQUIRED: The ZIP or other postal code of the address.</postal></cntaddr><cntvoice>REQUIRED: The telephone number by which individuals can speak to the organization or individual.</cntvoice></cntinfo></metc><metd Sync="TRUE">20060714</metd><metextns><metprof>LiDAR Acquisition Report</metprof><onlink>\\gisnw\vol1\Documentation\Projects\2005Ortho_LiDAR_Documentation\LiDAR 2005 Documentation\Acquisition\2005 LiDAR Acquisition Report\LiDAR_Report_final.doc</onlink></metextns><metextns><onlink>\\gisnw\vol1\Documentation\Projects\2005Ortho_LiDAR_Documentation\LiDAR 2005 Documentation\LiDAR Processing\LiDAR Validation Report\LiDAR_Vertical_AccuracyReportv2_2005.pdf</onlink><metprof>LiDAR Validation Report</metprof></metextns></metainfo><mdLang><languageCode Sync="TRUE" value="en"></languageCode></mdLang><mdStanName Sync="TRUE">ISO 19115 Geographic Information - Metadata</mdStanName><mdStanVer Sync="TRUE">DIS_ESRI1.0</mdStanVer><mdChar><CharSetCd Sync="TRUE" value="004"></CharSetCd></mdChar><mdHrLv><ScopeCd Sync="TRUE" value="005"></ScopeCd></mdHrLv><mdHrLvName Sync="TRUE">dataset</mdHrLvName><distinfo><resdesc Sync="TRUE">Downloadable Data</resdesc><stdorder><digform><digtinfo><transize Sync="TRUE">2.697</transize><dssize Sync="TRUE">2.697</dssize></digtinfo></digform></stdorder></distinfo><distInfo><distributor><distorTran><onLineSrc><orDesc Sync="TRUE">002</orDesc><linkage Sync="TRUE">file://\\BA204074\C$\New Personal Geodatabase.mdb</linkage><protocol Sync="TRUE">Local Area Network</protocol></onLineSrc><transSize Sync="TRUE">2.697</transSize></distorTran><distorFormat><formatName Sync="TRUE">Personal GeoDatabase Feature Class</formatName></distorFormat></distributor></distInfo><spdoinfo><direct Sync="TRUE">Vector</direct><ptvctinf><esriterm Name="BareEarth"><efeatyp Sync="TRUE">Simple</efeatyp><efeageom Sync="TRUE">Polygon</efeageom><esritopo Sync="TRUE">FALSE</esritopo><efeacnt Sync="TRUE">0</efeacnt><spindex Sync="TRUE">TRUE</spindex><linrefer Sync="TRUE">FALSE</linrefer></esriterm><sdtsterm Name="BareEarth"><sdtstype Sync="TRUE">G-polygon</sdtstype><ptvctcnt Sync="TRUE">0</ptvctcnt></sdtsterm></ptvctinf></spdoinfo><spatRepInfo><GridSpatRep><numDims Sync="TRUE">2</numDims><cellGeo><CellGeoCd Sync="TRUE" value="002"></CellGeoCd></cellGeo><tranParaAv Sync="TRUE">1</tranParaAv><axDimProps><Dimen><dimName><DimNameTypCd Sync="TRUE" value="002"></DimNameTypCd></dimName><dimSize Sync="TRUE">1000</dimSize><dimResol><value Sync="TRUE">6</value><uom><UomLength><uomName Sync="TRUE">unknown</uomName></UomLength></uom></dimResol></Dimen><Dimen><dimName><DimNameTypCd Sync="TRUE" value="001"></DimNameTypCd></dimName><dimSize Sync="TRUE">700</dimSize><dimResol><value Sync="TRUE">6</value><uom><UomLength><uomName Sync="TRUE">unknown</uomName></UomLength></uom></dimResol></Dimen></axDimProps></GridSpatRep><VectSpatRep><topLvl><TopoLevCd Sync="TRUE" value="001"></TopoLevCd></topLvl><geometObjs Name="BareEarth"><geoObjTyp><GeoObjTypCd Sync="TRUE" value="001"></GeoObjTypCd></geoObjTyp><geoObjCnt Sync="TRUE">0</geoObjCnt></geometObjs></VectSpatRep></spatRepInfo><spref><horizsys><cordsysn><projcsn>Maryland State Plane Zone </projcsn></cordsysn><geodetic><horizdn>NAD 83 HARN</horizdn></geodetic></horizsys><vertdef><altsys><altdatum>North American Vertical Datum of 1988</altdatum><altunits>feet</altunits><altenc>Implicit coordinate</altenc></altsys></vertdef></spref><mdDateSt Sync="TRUE">20060714</mdDateSt><dataqual><logic>The BE data is is supplied as an ASCII comma delimited file with each point represented with an  X, Y and elevation. The Bare Earth data is processed from the last return raw point cloud data.  This BE data is consistent with the original data.   Data were filtered using automated procedures followed by  manual editing to remove points that did not belong to the terrain surface (e.g. water, vegetation, buildings, system  (noise).</logic><complete>Sanborn and Dewberry performed various inspections of the BE data to ensure that each file contained points within the project limits.  Checks for correct tile naming were performed. 
The BE data generally may contain some voids where insufficient energy was reflected from the surface to generate a valid return from the terrain.  Voids tend to occur in heavily vegetated areas, water  bodies, and beneath buildings, motor vehicles, bridges, etc.. 
There were no gaps in the data due to insufficient side overlap or instrument malfunctions.</complete><posacc><horizpa><horizpar>LIDAR Bare Earth data were compared with airport surveyed elevations provided by Kinematic survey. The data and survey were compared and verified per project specifications. In addition, the Bare Earth Data was compared with the aerial photography stereo models used to provide breakline updates.
The horizontal accuracy of the GBEwas not tested explicitly. No accuracy statement is provided with the data.  Horizontal accuracy is measured in relation to the fit with the original Bare Earth LiDAR elevation data. The GBE data appears to conflate consistently with the original Bare Earth LiDAR data</horizpar></horizpa><vertacc><vertaccr>The vertical accuracy of the Bare Earth Data was checked using existing mapping control points used in the photo Aerial triangulation process. The comparison of the bare earth created TIN and the control points demonstrated an accuracy of shown below.  A quick contour line file is created to assist in locating discrepancies and anomolies in the BE data. A sample of  Bare Earth data tiles was compared in the 3D stereo models to judge data acceptability for future contouring. The data was acceptable in all instances.
Number               Easting     Northing   Known Z   Laser Z        Dz
-----------------------------------------------------------------------
GIS-110          1350813.790   663331.750   466.590   466.210    -0.380
GIS-111          1354555.470   680842.360   703.020   702.710    -0.310
GIS-112          1389046.060   681040.640   337.010   336.560    -0.450
GIS-113          1381576.310   694686.630   570.440   570.090    -0.350
GIS-114          1363682.150   707823.950   749.580   749.640    +0.060
GIS-115          1394911.030   711704.840   538.660   538.740    +0.080
GIS-116          1381543.600   721883.740   540.830   540.670    -0.160
GIS-117          1367855.830   729496.110   759.810   759.680    -0.130
GIS-118          1374751.930   747498.340   890.620   890.300    -0.320
GIS-119          1429547.650   748099.270   718.870   718.520    -0.350
GIS-120          1410208.930   726023.900   579.700   579.600    -0.100
GIS-121          1416795.020   712385.890   343.540   343.200    -0.340
GIS-122          1404031.000   701559.910   617.420   616.970    -0.450
GIS-123          1431285.510   706569.140   674.950   674.540    -0.410
GIS-124          1425001.750   707843.790   627.290   626.970    -0.320
GIS-125          1407895.490   684525.520   354.630   354.240    -0.390
GIS-126          1444187.450   689137.250   403.690   403.450    -0.240
GIS-127          1415619.970   693912.090   393.120   392.690    -0.430

Average dz           -0.277
Minimum dz           -0.450
Maximum dz           +0.080
Average magnitude     0.293
Root mean square      0.319
Std deviation         0.163</vertaccr></vertacc></posacc><lineage><procstep><srcused>Step 1</srcused><procdesc>Step 1- LIDAR data acquisition -- Sanborn flew the entire project area as a contiguous block of more than 870 square miles using the ALTM 2050 LIDAR sensor equipped with Airborne GPS and IMU positioning and orientation units. A total of 54 north-south flight lines and 90 east-west flight lines were required to cover the required entire County project area. 
Prior to data collection, two AGPS ground stations were established to support the LiDAR campaign.   NGS monument BELL (PID AJ7978) was used as the northern base station, while NGS monument MTN-B (PID AI4374) was used as the Martin State Airport base station.  The MTN-B point was used in a previous survey campaign completed by Sanborn in 2001.  Since the MTN-B point has only horizontal coordinates published, the vertical coordinates generated by the 2001 adjustment were used.  Point MTN-B is First Order horizontal, while BELL is Horizontal Order A and Vertical Order 2. We tied our network and adjusted our mini network vertically to a First Class I and five second Class II. The network accuracy is a function of the fully constrained adjustment and follows very closely the NOAA Technical Memorandum NOS NGS58 " Guidelines for Establishing GPS Derived Ellipsoid Heights (Standards: 2 cm and 5 cm)," November 1997 yielding sound network adjustment. The combination (Horizontal &amp; Vertical) achieved the height adjustment meeting the 5 cm standard. Adjustments constraints for the survey to derive the coordinates
The Optech ALTM (Airborne Laser Terrain Mapping) LiDAR system was calibrated regularly by conducting several passes over a flat surface of known elevaton at the job location.  Calibration flights were performed prior to and following every mission.  The calibration parameters were inserted into the post-processing software before final data processing. The observations used to establish the fiducial and survey point networks were made at various times during the LiDAR data collection period.  The LiDAR aircraft arrived on site March 18th  , 2005 and the LiDAR data collection was accomplished between March 18, 2005 and April 15,   2005.
 The flight plan for the project includes the following specifications to fully meet the project requirements.
"	Single pass density of approximately 1.0 square meters per sample 
"	Average area sampling density - 1.4 square meters per sample
"	Swath width 728 meters
"	 Flight altitude 1000 meters 
"	 Flight line spacing -589 meters with 125 meters overlap 
"	Scan Frequency- 35 Hz *Scan Angle- 20 degrees 
"	 Aircraft ground speed -- 140 knots 
"	 System Calibration pre and post mission 
"	Two GPS base stations within 30 KM.

The acquired LiDAR data was combined by flight line in a merge process that eliminated redundant points. The data was clipped into more manageable on KM by 1 KM tiles bounds. Noise, or anomalous returs were filtered from all data during this processing step. The data was quality check using commercial software TerraScan.</procdesc><proccont><cntinfo><cntperp><cntper>Mr. James Young </cntper><cntorg>Sanborn Map Company Inc.</cntorg></cntperp><cntpos>Project Engineer</cntpos><cntvoice>719-264-5602</cntvoice></cntinfo></proccont><procdate>05/2005- 03 /2006</procdate></procstep><procstep><srcused>Step 2</srcused><procdesc>Step 2- AGPS Processing and Point Cloud- First and Last Return Data Processing
Final post-processing of LiDAR data involves several steps.  The airborne GPS data were post-processed using Waypoint's GravNAVTM  software (version 6.03).  A fixed-bias carrier phase solution was computed in both the forward and reverse chronological directions.  All LiDAR acquisition was limited to periods when the PDOP was less than 4.0.
The GPS trajectory is combined with the raw IMU data and post-processed using Applanix Inc.'s POSPROC Kalman Filtering software.  This results in a two-fold improvement in the attitude accuracies over the real-time INS data.  The best estimated trajectory (BET) and refined attitude data are then re-introduced into the Optech REALM software to compute the laser point-positions - the trajectory is combined with the attitude data and laser range measurements to produce the 3-dimensional coordinates of the mass points.
The acquired LiDAR data was combined by flight line in a merge process that eliminated redundant points. The data was clipped into more manageable areas, 1 KM by 1 KM tiles bounds. Noise, or anomalous returns were filtered from all data during this processing step. The data was quality checked using commercial software TerraScan.</procdesc></procstep><procstep><procdesc>Step 3-- Elevation and Coordinate Processing.
All elevation data was processed on a point by point basis for ellipsoid to orthometric height conversion using the National Geodetic Survey (NGS) Geoid Model, GEOID99. Datum and coordinate system conversion from WGS84 to the Maryland State Plane coordinate system was performed using U.S. Army Corps of Engineers CorpsCon software algorithms. 



The LIDAR first and last return data is filtered to remove the vegetation and above ground manmade features. Computations are produced for both first and last laser return observations.  The ground-filtered delivery and corresponding regular grid DEM are produced from the last return data.  The first return information provides a useful depiction of the "canopy" within the project area.
Laser point filtering was accomplished using TerraScan LiDAR processing and modeling software.  The bare earth surface generated by TerraScan is used to produce regular grid DEMs.</procdesc><srcused>Step 3</srcused><procdate>2005</procdate></procstep><procstep><procdesc>Step 4 ESRI Bare Earth ASCII formating. 
The Terrscan  final processed bare earth data exported in ASCII comma delimited file format and clipped to the County' standard tile layout.  
837 Bare Earth  Data tiles was delivered on DVD media.
QC is performed</procdesc><srcused>Step 4</srcused><procdate>2005</procdate><procsv>TerraScan.</procsv></procstep><procstep><procdesc Sync="TRUE">Metadata imported.</procdesc><srcused Sync="TRUE">R:\Documentation\Projects\2005Ortho_LiDAR_Documentation\LiDAR 2005 Documentation\LiDAR Processing\LiDAR Metadata\LiDAR Bare Earth.xml</srcused><date Sync="TRUE">20060707</date><time Sync="TRUE">10404200</time></procstep><procstep><procdesc Sync="TRUE">Dataset copied.</procdesc><srcused Sync="TRUE">R:\Documentation\Projects\2005Ortho_LiDAR_Documentation\LiDAR 2005 Documentation\LiDAR Processing\LiDAR Metadata\New Personal Geodatabase.mdb</srcused><date Sync="TRUE">20060714</date><time Sync="TRUE">08281300</time></procstep></lineage><attracc><attraccr>There are three (3) attributes in the Bare Earth  files representing the horizontal coordinates and (Easting and Northing) and the vertical elevation all in feet. Sanborn has not supplied any explicit accuracy report for the BE values. Random inspection using 3D perspective views were made to ensure that the horizontal and vertical coordinate fell within the proper ranges and project limits. The BE values were not evaluated beyound a visual check for general consistency and completeness.</attraccr></attracc></dataqual><eainfo><detailed Name="BareEarth"><enttyp><enttypl Sync="TRUE">BareEarth</enttypl><enttypt Sync="TRUE">Feature Class</enttypt><enttypc Sync="TRUE">0</enttypc></enttyp><attr><attrlabl Sync="TRUE">OBJECTID</attrlabl><attalias Sync="TRUE">OBJECTID</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">OID</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">4</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale><attrdef Sync="TRUE">Internal feature number.</attrdef><attrdefs Sync="TRUE">ESRI</attrdefs><attrdomv><udom Sync="TRUE">Sequential unique whole numbers that are automatically generated.</udom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl Sync="TRUE">SHAPE</attrlabl><attalias Sync="TRUE">SHAPE</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Geometry</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">0</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale><attrdef Sync="TRUE">Feature geometry.</attrdef><attrdefs Sync="TRUE">ESRI</attrdefs><attrdomv><udom Sync="TRUE">Coordinates defining the features.</udom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl Sync="TRUE">SHAPE_Length</attrlabl><attalias Sync="TRUE">SHAPE_Length</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">8</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale><attrdef Sync="TRUE">Length of feature in internal units.</attrdef><attrdefs Sync="TRUE">ESRI</attrdefs><attrdomv><udom Sync="TRUE">Positive real numbers that are automatically generated.</udom></attrdomv></attr><attr><attrlabl Sync="TRUE">SHAPE_Area</attrlabl><attalias Sync="TRUE">SHAPE_Area</attalias><attrtype Sync="TRUE">Double</attrtype><attwidth Sync="TRUE">8</attwidth><atprecis Sync="TRUE">0</atprecis><attscale Sync="TRUE">0</attscale><attrdef Sync="TRUE">Area of feature in internal units squared.</attrdef><attrdefs Sync="TRUE">ESRI</attrdefs><attrdomv><udom Sync="TRUE">Positive real numbers that are automatically generated.</udom></attrdomv></attr></detailed></eainfo></metadata>
