<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE metadata SYSTEM "http://www.fgdc.gov/metadata/fgdc-std-001-1998.dtd">

<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
        <pubdate>201207</pubdate>
        <pubtime>Unknown</pubtime>
        <title>Hydro-Flattened Digital Elevation Models (DEMs)</title>
        <geoform>Elevation Data</geoform>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>Aerial Cartographics o America, Inc. collected LiDAR for over 681 square miles in Accomack, Dorchester, Somerset, Sussex, Wicomico, and Worchester Counties in Maryland, Deleware and Virginia.  The nominal pulse spacing for this project was no greater than 0.7 meters.  This project was collected with a Riegl LMS-Q680i Full Waveform LiDAR Sensor which collects  an intensity value, GPS Week Time, Flightline and echo number attributes for each discrete pulse .  Dewberry used proprietary procedures to classify the LAS into an initial ground surface.  Dewberry used proprietary procedures to classify the LAS and then performed manual classifications according to project specifications:  1-Unclassified, 2-Ground, 7-Noise, 9-Water,  and 10-Ignored Ground due to breakline proximity.  Dewberry produced 3D breaklines and combined these with the final LiDAR data to produce seamless DTMs, DSMs and hydro flattened DEMs,  for 833 tiles (1500 meters x 1500 meters) that cover the project area.</abstract>
      <purpose>The purpose of this LiDAR data was to produce high accuracy 3D elevation products, including tiled LiDAR in LAS 1.2 format, 3D breaklines, 1 meter cell size Digitial Surface Models(DSMs), 1 meter cell size Digital Terrain Models (DTMs), and1 meter cell size hydro flattened Digital Elevation Models (DEMs).  All products follow and comply with USGS v.13 specifications.</purpose>
      <supplinf>A complete description of this dataset is available in the Final Project Report submitted to the USGS.</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>20120214</begdate>
          <enddate>20120313</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>ground condition</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>As needed</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-76.079138</westbc>
        <eastbc>-75.438147</eastbc>
        <northbc>38.566941</northbc>
        <southbc>37.900496</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
        <themekey>DTM</themekey>
        <themekey>DSM</themekey>
        <themekey>Elevation</themekey>
        <themekey>Lidar</themekey>
        <themekey>LAS</themekey>
        <themekey>DEM</themekey>
        <themekey>Hydro Flattened</themekey>
        <themekey>Breaklines</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>None</placekt>
        <placekey>Maryland</placekey>
        <placekey>Dorchester County</placekey>
        <placekey>Wicomico County</placekey>
        <placekey>Worchester County</placekey>
        <placekey>Somerset County</placekey>
        <placekey>Delaware</placekey>
        <placekey>Sussex County</placekey>
        <placekey>Virginia</placekey>
        <placekey>Accomack County</placekey>
        <placekey>USA</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>This data was produced for the USGS according to specific project requirements.  This information is provided "as is".   Further documentation of this data can be obtained by contacting: USGS/NGTOC, 1400 Independence Road, Rolla, MO 65401.  Telephone (573) 308-3587.</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>USGS</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntpos>USGS NGTOC</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
          <address>1400 Independence Road</address>
          <city>Rolla</city>
          <state>MO</state>
          <postal>65401</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>(573) 308-3587</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>pemmett@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <native>Microsoft Windows XP Version 5.1 (Build 2600) Service Pack 3; ESRI ArcCatalog 10.0</native>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <logic>Data covers the tile scheme provided for the project area.</logic>
    <complete>A visual qualitative assessment was performed to ensure data completeness and full tiles. No void or missing data exists.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>The DEMs are derived from the source LiDAR and 3D breaklines created from the LiDAR.  Horizontal accuracy is not performed on the DEMs or breaklines.  Lidar source compiled to meet 1 meter horizontal accuracy.</horizpar>
        <qhorizpa>
          <horizpav>1 meter</horizpav>
          <horizpae>The DEMs are derived from the source LiDAR and 3D breaklines created from the LiDAR.  Horizontal accuracy is not performed on the DEMs, breaklines, or LiDAR.  LiDAR vendors perform calibrations on the LiDAR sensor and compare data to adjoing flight lines to ensure LiDAR meets the 1 meter horizontal accuracy standard at the 95% confidence level.  Please see the final project report delivered to the USGS for more details.</horizpae>
        </qhorizpa>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>The DEMs are derived from the source LiDAR and 3D breaklines created from the LiDAR.    

The vertical accuracy of the DEMs was tested by Dewberry with approximately 58 independent survey checkpoints.  The survey checkpoints were evenly distributed throughout the project area and were located in areas of open terrain, grass/weeds/crops, and forest.  

All  open terrain checkpoints were used to compute the Fundamental Vertical Accuracy (FVA).  Project specifications require a FVA of 0.182 meters based on a RMSEz (9.25 cm) x 1.9600.  All checkpoints in all land cover categories were used to compute the Consolidated Vertical Accuracy (CVA).  Project specifications require a CVA of 0.269 meters based on the 95th percentile.</vertaccr>
        <qvertpa>
          <vertaccv>0.157 meters</vertaccv>
          <vertacce>The DEMs are derived from the source LiDAR and 3D breaklines created from the LiDAR.  

Based on the vertical accuracy testing conducted by Dewberry, using NSSDA and FEMA methodology, vertical accuracy at the 95% confidence level (called Accuracyz) is computed by the formula RMSEz x 1.9600. The final DEM dataset for the USGS NRCS Maryland LiDAR project satisfies the criteria:
DEM dataset tested 0.157 meters vertical accuracy at 95% confidence level in open terrain, based on RMSEz (0.08 meters) x 1.9600.

Based on the vertical accuracy testing conducted by Dewberry, using NDEP and ASPRS methodology, consolidated vertical accuracy at the  95% confidence level is computed using the 95th percentile method.  The final DEM dataset for the USGS NRCS Maryland LiDAR project satisfies the criteria:
DEM dataset tested 0.267 meters vertical accuracy at 95% confidence level in all land cover categories combined.

These accuracy values are only slightly different from the accuracy results of the source LAS data because different interpolation methods are being used.  DEMs are created by averaging several LiDAR points within each pixel which may result in slightly different elevation values at each survey checkpoint when compared to the source LAS, which does not average several LiDAR points together but may interpolate (linearly) between two or three points to derive an elevation value.</vertacce>
        </qvertpa>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Data for the NRCS Maryland LiDAR project was acquired by Aerial Cartographics of America, Inc.

A Riegl LMS-Q680i Full Waveform LiDAR sensor was utilized to collect the data.  A calibration flight was flown on February 15, 2012 to obtain current boresight misalignment angles defining the relationship between the scanner and the Inertial Measurement Unit (IMU). A site was selected in Salisbury, Maryland. The 1320 ft X 1320ft site was surveyed to provide twelve (12) horizontal and vertical control locations for assessing the calibration. The area was flown at 1,600 feet AGL at 400 kHz with 50 percent sidelap in the recommended configuration of four (4) north south lines flown in alternating directions and four (4) east west lines flown in alternating directions. Refer to document NCRS Maryland Riegl Calibration.docx for additional information.
The project laser data were collected on February 17, 18, 23, 24 and March 12, 2012 utilizing a Riegl LMS-Q680i full waveform laser scanner (Serial Number 9997848) mounted in a Cessna 208 Grand Caravan aircraft at an approximate altitude of 3,300 feet above ground level (AGL) with a ground speed of 120 knots per hour, 30 percent sidelap, a pulse rate repetition (PRR) of 320 kHz, a scan half angle of 30 degrees resulting in a point spacing of 0.64 meters. The data were collected under cloud-, fog-, and snow-free conditions with no unusual flooding. No data were collected within 72 hours of rainfall that measured more than 0.25 inches. All data were acquired within 2 hours of low tide as predicted by tidal stations located on the bay and inland rivers. Tidal Stations used to determine tidal activity are Sharptown, Vienna, Salisbury, Roaring Point, Whitehaven, Great Shoals Light, Chance, Teague Creek, Long Point, Ewell, Crisfield, Ape Hole, and Shelltown

The GPS data from the ground base stations and the airborne platform were processed using Applanix POSPac 4.4 software module POSGPS. The Inertial Measurement Unit (IMU) solution was processed to provide information regarding the attitude of the sensor platform using the Applanix POSPac 4.4 software module POSProc. This solution was integrated with the Airborne GPS and adjusted using a Kalman filter in a forward/reverse solution to provide a Smoothed Best Estimate of Trajectory (SBET). The ground base stations were set up at the Salisbury-Ocean City Wicomico Regional Airport (ACA001) and on control point 111 enabling the aircraft to be within 25 miles of ground base station at all times.
Receivers for base station during Airborne Data Capture:

1. Leica GX123  464483 Dual frequency reciever
2. Leica AX1220GG 0632001 Dual Frequency GPS Antenna
3. Leica GX1230 464495 Dual Frequency GPS Reciever
4. Leica AX1220GG 0632002 Dual frequency GPS Antenna

Two base stations locations were used for the ABGPS processing 111 and ACA001, located at
the Salisbury Municipal airport.

1. station 111 easting 426121.404 northing 4216147.508 height 0.627
2. station ACA001 easting 343022.014 northing 4185037.17 height 38.948

Coordinate information for 13 aerial targets distributed throughout the project site was provided
by Greenman Pedersen Incorporated, Annapolis Junction, MD for ground validation. The
validation is for the acquisition portion of this project only. The control points were taken in flat,
open areas to determine a fundamental vertical accuracy.
Horizontal and vertical was established at the calibration site in Salisbury, Maryland and
throughout Somerset and Wicomico Counties on the Eastern Shore of Maryland.
The horizontal datum for the project is referenced to NAD 83 (2007), Maryland State Plane
Coordinate System, U.S. survey feet and UTM Zone 18, meters. The vertical datum for the
project is referenced to NAVD 88, U.S. survey feet and meters. Geoid 2009 was used as the
reference model for all GPS computations.

Using TerraSolid Ltd. software, an output control report was produced by comparing a triangulated irregular network of the laser points at the horizontal location of the known ground control points and measuring the vertical difference. The Vertical Root Mean Square Error (RMSEz) is 0.0246 meters. Accuracyz (RMSEz*1.96) is calculated at 0.048meters at 95% confidence level with no outliers.

The LiDAR data products collected for the project meet or exceed the requirements set out in the task order statement of work and specifications. All work was accomplished under the supervision of a Certified Photogrammetrist as recognized by the American Society for Photogrammetry and Remote Sensing.</procdesc>
        <srcused>Airborne Global Positioning System Data</srcused>
        <srcused>Inertial Measurement Unit</srcused>
        <procdate>201203</procdate>
        <srcprod>Calibrated LiDAR Point Cloud LAS 1.2 format</srcprod>
        <proccont>
          <cntinfo>
            <cntorgp>
              <cntorg>Aerial Cartographics of America, Inc</cntorg>
            </cntorgp>
            <cntaddr>
              <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
              <address>1722 West Oakridge Road</address>
              <city>Orlando</city>
              <state>FL</state>
              <postal>32809</postal>
              <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>1.407.851.7880</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>1.407.855.8250</cntfax>
            <hours>Monday to Friday, 8 - 4, CST</hours>
          </cntinfo>
        </proccont>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Dewberry utilizes a variety of software suites for inventory management, classification, and data processing. All LiDAR related processes begin by importing the data into the GeoCue task management software.  The swath data is tiled according to project specifications (1,500 m x 1,500 m).  The tiled data is then opened in Terrascan where Dewberry uses proprietary ground classification routines to remove any non-ground points and generate an accurate ground surface.  The ground routine consists of three main parameters (building size, iteration angle, and iteration distance); by adjusting these parameters and running several iterations of this routine an initial ground surface is developed. The building size parameter sets a roaming window size. Each tile is loaded with neighboring points from adjacent tiles and the routine classifies the data section by section based on this roaming window size. The second most important parameter is the maximum terrain angle, which sets the highest allowed terrain angle within the model. Once the ground routine has been completed a manual quality control routine is done using hillshades, cross-sections, and profiles within the Terrasolid software suite. After this QC step, a peer review and supervisor manual inspection is completed on a percentage of the classified tiles based on the project size and variability of the terrain. After the ground classification corrections were completed, the dataset was processed through a water classification routine that utilizes breaklines compiled by Dewberry to automatically classify hydrographic features.  The water classification routine selects ground points within the breakline polygons and automatically classifies them as class 9, water. During this water classification routine, points that are within 1 meter of the hydrographic features are moved to class 10, an ignored ground due to breakline proximity. In addition to classes 1, 2, 9, and 10, there is a Class 7, noise points . This class was only used if needed when points could manually be identified as low/high points. 
 
The fully classified dataset is then processed through Dewberry's comprehensive quality control program.   

The data was classified as follows:
Class 1 = Unclassified.  This class includes vegetation, buildings, noise etc.
Class 2 = Ground
Class 7= Noise
Class 9 = Water
Class 10=Ignored


The LAS header information was verified to contain the following:
Class (Integer)
GPS Week Time (0.0001 seconds)
Easting (0.003 m)
Northing (0.003 m)
Elevation (0.003 m)
Echo Number (Integer 1 to 4)
Echo (Integer 1 to 4)
Intensity (8 bit integer)
Flight Line (Integer)
Scan Angle (Integer degree)</procdesc>
        <srcused>Calibrated LiDAR Point Cloud LAS 1.2 format</srcused>
        <procdate>201204</procdate>
        <srcprod>Tiled LiDAR datasets with initial ground classification</srcprod>
        <proccont>
          <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
              <cntorg>Dewberry - Geospatial Services Group</cntorg>
              <cntper>Amar Nayegandhi</cntper>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Project Manager</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
              <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
              <address>1000 N. Ashley Drive, Suite 801</address>
              <city>Tampa</city>
              <state>FL</state>
              <postal>33602</postal>
              <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>813.421.8642</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>813.225.1385</cntfax>
            <cntemail>anayegandhi@dewberry.com</cntemail>
            <hours>8:00 - 5:00 EST</hours>
          </cntinfo>
        </proccont>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Dewberry used GeoCue software to develop raster stereo models from the LiDAR intensity.  The raster resolution was 0.3 meters.</procdesc>
        <srcused>Final LiDAR datasets with USGS v13 classifications</srcused>
        <procdate>201205</procdate>
        <srcprod>Lidar Intensity Stereopairs</srcprod>
        <proccont>
          <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
              <cntorg>Dewberry - Geospatial Services Group</cntorg>
              <cntper>Amar Nayegandhi</cntper>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Project Manager</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
              <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
              <address>1000 N. Ashley Drive, Suite 801</address>
              <city>Tampa</city>
              <state>FL</state>
              <postal>33602</postal>
              <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>813.421.8642</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>813.225.1385</cntfax>
            <cntemail>anayegandhi@dewberry.com</cntemail>
            <hours>8:00 - 5:00 EST</hours>
          </cntinfo>
        </proccont>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>LiDAR intensity stereopairs were viewed in 3-D stereo using Socet Set for ArcGIS softcopy photogrammetric software. The breaklines are collected directly into an ArcGIS file geodatabase to ensure correct topology.  The LiDARgrammetry was performed under the direct supervision of an ASPRS Certified Photogrammetrist.  The breaklines were  stereo-compiled  in accordance with the Data Dictionary.  

Inland Lakes and Ponds,  Inland Streams and Rivers and Tidal Waters were collected according to specifications for the NRCS Maryland LiDAR Project.</procdesc>
        <srcused>Lidar Intensity Stereopairs</srcused>
        <procdate>201206</procdate>
        <srcprod>3D breaklines</srcprod>
        <proccont>
          <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
              <cntorg>Dewberry</cntorg>
              <cntper>Amar Nayegandhi</cntper>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Project Manager</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
              <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
              <address>1000 N. Ashley Drive, Suite 801</address>
              <city>Tampa</city>
              <state>FL</state>
              <postal>33602</postal>
              <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>813.421.8642</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>813.225.1385</cntfax>
            <cntemail>anayegandhi@dewberry.com</cntemail>
            <hours>8:00 - 4:00 EST</hours>
          </cntinfo>
        </proccont>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Class 2, ground, LiDAR points are exported from the LAS files into an Arc Geodatabase (GDB) in multipoint format.  The 3D breaklines, Inland Lakes and Ponds and Inland Streams and Rivers, are imported into the same GDB.  An ESRI Terrain is generated from these inputs.  The surface type of each input is as follows:

Ground Multipoint:  Masspoints
Inland Lakes and Ponds:  Hard Replace
Inland Streams and Rivers:  Hard Line
Tidal: Hard Line</procdesc>
        <srcused>Lidar Ground Points, Class 2</srcused>
        <srcused>3D Breaklines</srcused>
        <procdate>201206</procdate>
        <srcprod>ESRI Terrain</srcprod>
        <proccont>
          <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
              <cntorg>Dewberry</cntorg>
              <cntper>Amar Nayegandhi</cntper>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Project Manager</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
              <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
              <address>1000 N. Ashley Drive, Suite 801</address>
              <city>Tampa</city>
              <state>FL</state>
              <postal>33602</postal>
              <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>813.421.8642</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>813.225.1385</cntfax>
            <cntemail>anayegandhi@dewberry.com</cntemail>
            <hours>8:00 - 4:00 EST</hours>
          </cntinfo>
        </proccont>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>The ESRI Terrain is converted to rasters.  The rasters are created to pre-defined extents so that multiple rasters are created over the project area.  Creating multiple rasters rather than one large raster over a large project area makes the data more maneageable to work with.  The rasters are created with 2 tiles of overlap.  This allows us to ensure seamless coverage and edge-matching in the final tiled product.  These rasters were created with a 1 meter cell size.</procdesc>
        <srcused>ESRI Terrain</srcused>
        <procdate>201207</procdate>
        <srcprod>Non-Tiled Hydro Flattened DEMs</srcprod>
        <proccont>
          <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
              <cntorg>Dweberry</cntorg>
              <cntper>Amar Nayegandhi</cntper>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Project Manager</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
              <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
              <address>1000 N. Ashley Drive, Suite 801</address>
              <city>Tampa</city>
              <state>FL</state>
              <postal>33602</postal>
              <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>813.421.8642</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>813.225.1385</cntfax>
            <cntemail>anayegandhi@dewberry.com</cntemail>
            <hours>8:00 - 4:00 EST</hours>
          </cntinfo>
        </proccont>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>The DEMs that are created over large areas are reviewed in ArcGIS with hillshades and in Global Mapper.  Hillshades allow the analyst to view the DEMs in 3D and to more efficiently locate and identify potential issues.  The first review is done on the area DEMs as this increases the efficiency of any corrections that may be performed.  Performing corrections on area DEMs allows the analyst to perform corrections on multiple tiles at once and helps prevent errors from occurring along individual tile seamlines.  Analysts review the area DEMs for incorrect  water elevations and artifacts that are introduced during the raster creation process.</procdesc>
        <srcused>Non-Tiled Hydro Flattened DEMs</srcused>
        <procdate>201207</procdate>
        <srcprod>Corrected and Final Non-Tiled Hydro Flattened DEMs</srcprod>
        <proccont>
          <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
              <cntorg>Dewberry</cntorg>
              <cntper>Amar Nayegandhi</cntper>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Project Manager</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
              <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
              <address>1000 N. Ashley Drive, Suite 801</address>
              <city>Tampa</city>
              <state>FL</state>
              <postal>33602</postal>
              <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>813.421.8642</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>813.225.1385</cntfax>
            <cntemail>anayegandhi@dewberry.com</cntemail>
            <hours>8:00 - 4:00 EST</hours>
          </cntinfo>
        </proccont>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>he corrected and final area DEMs are clipped to individual tiles.  Dewberry uses a proprietary tool that clips the area DEMs to each tile located within the final Tile Grid, names the clipped DEM to the Tile Grid Cell name, and verifies that final extents are correct.  All individual tiles are loaded into Global Mapper for the last review.  During this last review, an analsyt checks to ensure full, complete coverage, no issues along tile boundaries, tiles seamlessly edge-match, and that there are no remaining processing artifacts in the dataset.</procdesc>
        <srcused>Corrected and Final Non-Tiled Hydro Flattened DEMs</srcused>
        <procdate>201207</procdate>
        <srcprod>Final Tiled Hydro Flattened DEMs</srcprod>
        <proccont>
          <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
              <cntorg>Dewberry</cntorg>
              <cntper>Amar Nayegandhi</cntper>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Project Manager</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
              <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
              <address>1000 N. Ashley Drive, Suite 801</address>
              <city>Tampa</city>
              <state>FL</state>
              <postal>33602</postal>
              <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>813.421.8642</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>813.225.1385</cntfax>
            <cntemail>anayegandhi@dewberry.com</cntemail>
            <hours>8:00 - 4:00 EST</hours>
          </cntinfo>
        </proccont>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <direct>Raster</direct>
    <rastinfo>
      <rasttype>Grid Cell</rasttype>
      <rowcount>73500</rowcount>
      <colcount>45000</colcount>
      <vrtcount>1</vrtcount>
    </rastinfo>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <mapproj>
          <mapprojn>Transverse Mercator</mapprojn>
          <transmer>
            <sfctrmer>0.999600</sfctrmer>
            <longcm>-75.000000</longcm>
            <latprjo>0.000001</latprjo>
            <feast>500000.000000</feast>
            <fnorth>0.000001</fnorth>
          </transmer>
        </mapproj>
        <planci>
          <plance>coordinate pair</plance>
          <coordrep>
            <absres>0.000100</absres>
            <ordres>0.000100</ordres>
          </coordrep>
          <plandu>meters</plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>D_NAD_1983_NSRS2007</horizdn>
        <ellips>Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips>
        <semiaxis>6378137.000000</semiaxis>
        <denflat>298.257222</denflat>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
    <vertdef>
      <altsys>
        <altdatum>North American Vertical Datum of 1988</altdatum>
        <altres>0.000100</altres>
        <altunits>meter</altunits>
        <altenc>Explicit elevation coordinate included with horizontal coordinates</altenc>
      </altsys>
    </vertdef>
  </spref>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>USGS</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntpos>USGS NGTOC</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
          <address>1400 Independence Road</address>
          <city>Rolla</city>
          <state>MO</state>
          <postal>65401</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>(573) 308-3587</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>pemmett@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <resdesc>Downloadable Data</resdesc>
    <distliab>This data was produced for the USGS according to specific project requirements.  This information is provided "as is".   Further documentation of this data can be obtained by contacting: USGS/NGTOC, 1400 Independence Road, Rolla, MO 65401.  Telephone (573) 308-3587.</distliab>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20120727</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>USGS</cntorg>
          <cntper>Patrick Emmett</cntper>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntpos>USGS NGTOC</cntpos>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
          <address>1400 Independence Road</address>
          <city>Rolla</city>
          <state>MO</state>
          <postal>65401</postal>
          <country>USA</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>(573) 308-3587</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>pemmett@usgs.gov</cntemail>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Content Standards for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
    <mettc>local time</mettc>
    <metextns>
      <onlink>http://www.esri.com/metadata/esriprof80.html</onlink>
      <metprof>ESRI Metadata Profile</metprof>
    </metextns>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>

