<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE metadata SYSTEM "http://www.fgdc.gov/metadata/fgdc-std-001-1998.dtd"[]>
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>Washington County - FEMA Region 3 FY12 LiDAR</origin>
        <pubdate>201207</pubdate>
        <pubtime>Unknown</pubtime>
        <title>Project</title>
        <geoform>map</geoform>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>Dewberry collected LiDAR for ~3,942 square miles in various Virginia, West Virigia, and Maryland Counties. The acquisition was performed by Geodigital. This metadata covers the LiDAR produced for the Washington County project area. The nominal pulse spacing for this project is 1.6 ft (0.5 meters). This project was collected with a sensor which collects intensity values for each discrete pulse extracted from the waveform. GPS Week Time, Intensity, Flightline and echo number attributes were provided for each LiDAR point.  Dewberry used proprietary procedures to classify the LAS according to contract specifications:  1-Unclassified, 2-Ground, 7-Noise, 9-Water, 10-Ignored Ground due to breakline proximity, and 11-Withheld.  Dewberry produced 3D breaklines and combined these with the final LiDAR data to produce seamless hydro flattened DEMs for the 638 tiles (1500 m x 1500 m) that cover the this deliverable.</abstract>
      <purpose>The purpose of this LiDAR data was to produce high accuracy 3D elevation products, including tiled LiDAR in LAS 1.2 format, 3D breaklines, and a 1 m cell size hydro flattened Digital Elevation Models (DEM).</purpose>
      <supplinf>A complete description of this dataset is available in the Final Project Report.</supplinf>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
        <rngdates>
          <begdate>20120131</begdate>
          <enddate>20120327</enddate>
        </rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>ground condition</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>As needed</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
        <westbc>-78.383395</westbc>
        <eastbc>-77.442101</eastbc>
        <northbc>39.723097</northbc>
        <southbc>39.327819</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
        <themekey>DTM</themekey>
        <themekey>Elevation</themekey>
        <themekey>Lidar</themekey>
        <themekey>LAS</themekey>
        <themekey>DEM</themekey>
        <themekey>Hydro Flattened</themekey>
        <themekey>Breaklines</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>None</placekt>
        <placekey>Washington</placekey>
        <placekey>Maryland</placekey>
        <placekey>United States of America</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>This data was produced for the USGS and FEMA according to specific project requirements.  This information is provided "as is".   Further documentation of this data can be obtained by contacting: Patrick Emmett, MS 666, 1400 Independence Road, Rolla, MO 65401. Telephone (573) 308-3587.</useconst>
    <ptcontac>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>USGS</cntorg>
          <cntper>Patrick Emmett</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
          <address>MS 666, 1400 Independence Road</address>
          <city>Rolla</city>
          <state>Missouri</state>
          <postal>65401</postal>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>573.308.3810</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>pemmett@usgs.gov</cntemail>
        <hours>8:00 AM - 5:00 PM</hours>
      </cntinfo>
    </ptcontac>
    <native>Microsoft Windows Server 2008 R2 Version 6.1 (Build 7601) Service Pack 1; ESRI ArcCatalog 10.0.0.2414</native>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <logic>Data covers the tile scheme provided for the project area.</logic>
    <complete>A visual qualitative assessment was performed to ensure data completeness and bare earth data cleanliness. No void or missing data, the bare earth surface is of good quality and data passes vertical accuracy specifications.</complete>
    <posacc>
      <horizpa>
        <horizpar>Lidar source compiled to meet 1 meter horizontal accuracy at the 95 percent confidence level.</horizpar>
        <qhorizpa>
          <horizpae>Dewberry does not perform independent horizontal accuracy testing on the LiDAR.  LiDAR vendors perform calibrations on the LiDAR sensor and compare data to adjoing flight lines to ensure LiDAR meets the 1 meter horizontal accuracy standard at the 95% confidence level.  Please see the final project report for more details.</horizpae>
          <horizpav>3.28 ft</horizpav>
        </qhorizpa>
      </horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>The vertical accuracy of the DEMs was tested by Dewberry with 116 independently collected checkpoints. The survey checkpoints are distributed throughout the project area. These 116 checkpoints contain 28 open terrain points, 12 crops/weeds points, 24 forested points, 27 urban points, and 25 points located around brush lands and trees. The 116 checkpoints were used to compute the Fundamental Vertical Accuracy (FVA) and the Consolidated Vertical Accuracy (CVA). Project specifications required a FVA of 0.245 meters for open terrain and a CVA of 0.363 meters. 

Appendix A, Guidance for Aerial Mapping and Surveying, to FEMA’s “Guidelines and Specifications for Flood Hazard Mapping Partners” requires a minimum of 60 test points -- 20 each in a minimum of three land cover categories representative of the floodplain. FEMA’s Procedure Memorandum No. 61 – “Standards for Lidar and Other High Quality Digital Topography” -- specifies that the positional accuracy of LiDAR shall be in accordance with ASPRS/NDEP standards for accuracy testing as well as the USGS “Lidar Guidelines and Base Specifications, v13.”  All of these standards and guidelines require testing for Fundamental Vertical Accuracy (FVA), Supplemental Vertical Accuracy (SVA), and Consolidated Vertical Accuracy (CVA), using a minimum of 20 checkpoints each in a minimum of three land cover categories for a minimum total of 60 QA/QC checkpoints.</vertaccr>
        <qvertpa>
          <vertaccv>0.10 meters</vertaccv>
          <vertacce>This RMSE analysis was performed on the DEMs. Based on the vertical accuracy testing conducted by Dewberry, using NSSDA and FEMA methodology, vertical accuracy at the 95% confidence level (called Accuracyz) is computed by the formula RMSEz x 1.9600. The dataset for the project area satisfies the criteria: Lidar dataset tested 0.20 meters vertical accuracy at 95% confidence level, based on RMSEz (0.10 ft) x 1.9600. The Consolidated Vertical Acccuracy is 0.25 meters.</vertacce>
        </qvertpa>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
      <srcinfo>
        <srccite>
          <citeinfo>
            <origin>Dewberry</origin>
            <pubdate>20120727</pubdate>
            <title>Washington County - FEMA Region 3 FY 12 LiDAR</title>
            <edition>One</edition>
            <geoform>map</geoform>
            <pubinfo>
              <pubplace>Fairfax, VA</pubplace>
              <publish>Dewberry</publish>
            </pubinfo>
            <onlink>www.dewberry.com</onlink>
          </citeinfo>
        </srccite>
        <typesrc>Hard Drive</typesrc>
        <srctime>
          <timeinfo>
            <rngdates>
              <begdate>20120131</begdate>
              <enddate>20120327</enddate>
            </rngdates>
          </timeinfo>
          <srccurr>Ground Condition</srccurr>
        </srctime>
        <srccitea>none</srccitea>
        <srccontr>LiDAR data representing FEMA Region 3FT Task Order to be used for various analyses and research purposes.</srccontr>
      </srcinfo>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>
- Establishment of survey points to support the LiDAR data collection. six existing published NGS stations (AI6312, AJ8025, DM6144, HV3503, JV4103, JV6141) were observed in a GPS control network and used to establish five new points for the primary control for this site. AI6312, AJ8025, DM6144, HV3503, JV4103, JV6141, 335DEW09, 335DEW10, 335DEW20, 335DEW21, 335DEW22 were observed and used to control all flight missions and static ground surveys. The following are the final coordinates of the control points used for this project: SurveyBlock, Station, Latitude(D M S Hem), Longitude(D M S Hem), H-Ell(m), H-MSL(m) 335_DEW_11, 335DEW09, 39 02 32.49529, -77 31 34.98309, 91.1625, 123.3164 335_DEW_11, 335DEW10, 38 45 06.58533, -77 44 53.11093, 105.8415, 138.0279 335_DEW_11, 335DEW20, 39 33 44.04655, -78 37 05.79616, 152.4477, 185.5792 335_DEW_11, 335DEW21, 39 24 00.80394, -78 04 35.85693, 204.8443, 238.8695 335_DEW_11, 335DEW22, 39 29 36.03322, -77 34 08.01429, 150.5777, 183.7722 335_DEW_11, AI6312, 39 41 43.29694, -78 47 16.08769, 182.8978, 215.3993 335_DEW_11, AJ8025, 39 17 34.38480, -77 18 53.40005, 146.1161, 178.2409 335_DEW_11, DM6144, 38 35 08.87989, -77 42 43.87127, 64.7557, 96.8580 335_DEW_11, HV3503, 38 58 29.39869, -77 41 26.89214, 109.6036, 141.9908 335_DEW_11, JV4103, 39 32 18.83476, -77 59 06.07081, 122.8047, 157.0112 335_DEW_11, JV6141, 39 04 51.93707, -77 33 30.18563, 81.9107, 114.2138			                            
				</procdesc>
        <srcused>Published_NGS_Coordinates</srcused>
        <srcused>Raw_Control_GPS</srcused>
        <procdate>201201</procdate>
        <srcprod>Control_Network</srcprod>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>- Airborne acquisition of Lidar GeoDigital used two Optech ALTM 3100EA system to collect the data. The Optech System was configured in the following method: Aircraft Speed 150 knots Data Acquisition Height 950 m AGL Swath Width 680.00 m Distance between Flight Lines 470.00 m Overlap 30 % Scanner Field Of View 22 +/- degrees (+/-2 degrees flagged as withheld) Pulse Repetition Rate 70 KHz Scan Frequency 40 Hz Number of Returns per Pulse 4 Discrete returns Beam Divergence 0.3 mRad Flight Line Length shorter than 70km Base Station Distance shorter than 40km Resultant Raw Point Density ~1 pt/m2 with overlap Aircraft Speed 150 knots Data Acquisition Height 950 m AGL Swath Width 680.00 m Distance between Flight Lines 350.00 m Overlap 55 % Scanner Field Of View 22 +/- degrees (+/-2 degrees flagged as withheld) Pulse Repetition Rate 70 KHz Scan Frequency 40 Hz Number of Returns per Pulse 4 Discrete returns Beam Divergence 0.3 mRad Flight Line Length shorter than 70km Base Station Distance shorter than 40km Resultant Raw Point Density ~1 pt/m2 with overlap Aircraft platforms were used in the collection of this project: A Cessna 310 aircraft was used to conduct the aerial survey. The Cessna 310 is a fixed wing aircraft that have an endurance of approximately 5 hours. -GPS-IMU: High accuracy IMU (200Hz) and GPS information (1Hz) concerning the attitude and position of the sensor were acquired at the same time as the Laser data. Ground based GPS stations also acquired consecutive GPS information for the duration of the flights. A combination of Sokkia GSR 2600 and NovAtel DL-4+ dual-frequency GPS receivers were used to support the airborne operations of this survey.                    
  
- Flights and Flight Lines The area is covered by several missions, a mission is defined as the block of acquisition between aircraft take-off and landing flown under good meteorological and GPS conditions, and each mission includes multiple flightlines. 

List of Base Stations: JV6141
Number of Missions: 25
List Of Missions: o112031a, o112031b, o112034a, o112034a, o112034b, o112050b, o112051a, o112051b, o112053a, o112057a, o112057b, o112066a, o112070a, o112070b, o112071a, o112071b, 0112072a, o112072b, o112073a, o112073b, o112082a, o112083a, o112083b, o112086a 

</procdesc>
        <procdate>201201</procdate>
        <srcprod>Raw_GPS_IMU</srcprod>
        <srcprod>Raw_Lidar</srcprod>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>
- Airborne GPS Kinematic processing
Airborne GPS kinematic data was processed on-site using GrafNav kinematic On-The-Fly (OTF) software. Flights were flown with a minimum of 6 satellites in view (13 degrees above the horizon) and with a PDOP of better than 4. Distances from base station to aircraft were kept to a maximum of 40 km, to ensure a strong OTF (On-The-Fly) solution. For all flights, the GPS data can be classified as excellent, with GPS residuals of 3cm average but no larger than 10 cm being recorded.

The Geoid09 geoid model, published by the NGS, was used to transform all ellipsoidal heights to orthometric.
</procdesc>
        <srcused>Control_Network</srcused>
        <srcused>Raw_GPS_IMU</srcused>
        <procdate>201203</procdate>
        <srcprod>Processed_Trajectory</srcprod>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>
- Generation and Calibration of laser points
Laser data points are generated using Optech's software Dashmap.  Those software combine the raw laser range and angle data file with the finalized GPS/IMU trajectory information. 
Each mission is evaluated in Terrasolid's Terramatch software to correct any residual roll pitch heading misalignments, if necessary those values are to the data. 
The resulting point cloud is projected into the desired coordinate system and created in LAS format. One file per swath, files bigger than 2Gb split in 2.
On a project level, a coverage check is carried out to ensure no slivers are present.

</procdesc>
        <srcused>Raw_Lidar</srcused>
        <srcused>Processed_Trajectory</srcused>
        <procdate>201203</procdate>
        <srcprod>Calibrated_LiDAR</srcprod>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>
- Mission to mission adjustments of Lidar data
All missions are validated and adjusted against the adjoining
missions for relative vertical biases and collected GPS static and kinematic
ground truthing points for absolute vertical accuracy purposes.
</procdesc>
        <srcused>Calibrated_LiDAR</srcused>
        <procdate>201203</procdate>
        <srcprod>Calibrated_LiDAR_VertAdj</srcprod>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>
- Deliverable Product Generation

*Raw Calibrated LIDAR Point Cloud
Raw LiDAR point cloud, was provided in the following formats/parameters:
- LAS V1.2, point record format 1, Adjusted GPS time, georeferencing information populated in header
- The following fields are included in the LAS file:
1. Adjusted GPS time reported to the nearest microsecond
2. Flight line ID
3. Easting (reported to the nearest 0.01 m)
4. Northing  (reported to the nearest 0.01 m)
5. Elevation (reported to the nearest 0.01 m)
6. intensity
7. Echo number
8. Classification
9. Scan angle
10. Edge of scan
11. Scan direction
- Full swaths, all collected points delivered (except discarded flightline)
- The Withheld bit flags the last 2 degrees of the swath (Additional areas are classified with the withheld in areas where wind or vegetation affected the quality of the data long the edge of the flight line.  The classification of the additional withheld areas does not affect the density of the data.)
- 1 file per swath, 1 swath per file (except when swath had to be divided in section for size or calibration)

</procdesc>
        <srcused>VertAdj_Calibrated_LiDAR</srcused>
        <procdate>201204</procdate>
        <srcprod>Client_deliverables</srcprod>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Dewberry utilizes a variety of software suites for inventory management, classification, and data processing. All LiDAR related processes begin by importing the data into the GeoCue task management software. GeoCue allows the data to retain its delivered tiling scheme (1500 m by 1500 m). The tiled data is then opened in Terrascan where Dewberry uses proprietary ground classification routines to remove any non-ground points and generate an accurate ground surface. The ground routine consists of three main parameters (building size, iteration angle, and iteration distance); by adjusting these parameters and running several iterations of this routine an initial ground surface is developed. The building size parameter sets a roaming window size. Each tile is loaded with neighboring points from adjacent tiles and the routine classifies the data section by section based on this roaming window size. The second most important parameter is the maximum terrain angle, which sets the highest allowed terrain angle within the model. Once the ground routine has been completed a manual quality control routine is done using hillshades, cross-sections, and profiles within the Terrasolid software suite. After this QC step, a peer review and supervisor manual inspection is completed on a percentage of the classified tiles based on the project size and variability of the terrain. After the ground classification corrections were completed, the dataset was processed through a water classification routine that utilizes breaklines compiled by Dewberry to automatically classify hydrographic features.  The water classification routine selects ground points within the breakline polygons and automatically classifies them as class 9, water. During this water classification routine, points which are in close proximity (1 m) to the hydrographic features are moved to class 10, an ignored ground. In addition to classes 1, 2, 8, 9, and 10, the project allows for a Class 7, noise points. This class was only used if needed when points could manually be identified as low/high points. Dewberry also used Class 11 - Withheld points.
The fully classified dataset is then processed through Dewberry's comprehensive quality control program.

The data was classified as follows:
Class 1 = Unclassified.  This class includes vegetation, buildings, noise etc.
Class 2 = Ground
Class 7 = Noise
Class 8 = Model Key Points
Class 9 = Water
Class 10 = Ignored Ground
Class 11 = Withheld

The LAS header information was verified to contain the following:
Class (Integer)
GPS Week Time (0.0001 seconds)
Easting (0.01 m)
Northing (0.01 m)
Elevation (0.01 m)
Echo Number (Integer 1 to 4)
Echo (Integer 1 to 4)
Intensity (8 bit integer)
Flight Line (Integer)
Scan Angle (Integer degree)</procdesc>
        <srcused>Processed Lidar datasets in LAS 1.2 format</srcused>
        <procdate>201206</procdate>
        <srcprod>Finalized LiDAR dataset using Orthometric Heights.</srcprod>
        <proccont>
          <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
              <cntper>Keith Patterson</cntper>
              <cntorg>Dewberry - Geospatial Services Group</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Project Manager</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
              <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
              <address>1000 N. Ashley Drive, Suite 801</address>
              <city>Tampa</city>
              <state>FL</state>
              <postal>33602</postal>
              <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>813.421.8635</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>813.225.1385</cntfax>
            <cntemail>kpatterson@dewberry.com</cntemail>
            <hours>8:00 - 5:00 EST</hours>
          </cntinfo>
        </proccont>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Dewberry used GeoCue software to develop raster stereo models from the LiDAR intensity.  The raster resolution was 1 meter.</procdesc>
        <srcused>Finalized LiDAR dataset using Orthometric Heights.</srcused>
        <procdate>201206</procdate>
        <srcprod>Lidar Intensity Stereopairs</srcprod>
        <proccont>
          <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
              <cntper>Keith Patterson</cntper>
              <cntorg>Dewberry - Geospatial Services Group</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Project Manager</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
              <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
              <address>1000 N. Ashley Drive, Suite 801</address>
              <city>Tampa</city>
              <state>FL</state>
              <postal>33602</postal>
              <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>813.421.8635</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>813.225.1385</cntfax>
            <cntemail>kpatterson@dewberry.com</cntemail>
            <hours>8:00 - 5:00 EST</hours>
          </cntinfo>
        </proccont>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>LiDAR intensity stereopairs were viewed in 3-D stereo using Socet Set for ArcGIS softcopy photogrammetric software. The breaklines are collected directly into an ArcGIS file geodatabase to ensure correct topology.  The LiDARgrammetry was performed under the direct supervision of an ASPRS Certified Photogrammetrist.  The breaklines were  stereo-compiled  in accordance with the Data Dictionary.  

The data dictionary defines Tidal Waters as the land and water interface at the time of LiDAR acquisition of tidally influenced bodies of water.  There is no minimum area requirement.  Tidal variations over the course of a collection or between different collections will result in discontinuities along shorelines.  This is considered normal and these "anomalies" should be retained.  Variations in water surface elevation resulting in tidal variations during a collection should NOT be removed or adjusted, as this would require either the removal of valid, measured ground points or the introduction of unmeasured ground into the DEM.  The USGS priority is on the ground surface, and accepts there may be occasional, unavoidable irregularities in water surface.

Breaklines must be captured at or just below the elevations of the immediately surrounding terain.  Under no circumstances should a feature be elevated above the surrounding LiDAR points.

If it can be reasonably determined where the edge of water most probably falls, beneath the dock or pier, then the edge of water will be collected at the elevation of the water where it can be directly measured. If there is a clearly-indicated headwall or bulkhead adjacent to the dock or pier and it is evident that the waterline is most probably adjacent to the headwall or bulkhead, then the water line will follow the headwall or bulkhead at the elevation of the water where it can be directly measured. If there is no clear indication of the location of the waters edge beneath the dock or pier, then the edge of water will follow the outer edge of the dock or pier as it is adjacent to the water, at the measured elevation of the water.

Breaklines shall snap and merge seamlessly with linear hydrographic features.</procdesc>
        <srcused>Lidar Intensity Stereopairs</srcused>
        <procdate>201206</procdate>
        <srcprod>3D breaklines</srcprod>
        <proccont>
          <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
              <cntper>Keith Patterson</cntper>
              <cntorg>Dewberry - Geospatial Services Group</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Project Manager</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
              <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
              <address>1000 N. Ashley Drive, Suite 801</address>
              <city>Tampa</city>
              <state>FL</state>
              <postal>33602</postal>
              <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>813.421.8635</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>813.225.1385</cntfax>
            <cntemail>kpatterson@dewberry.com</cntemail>
            <hours>8:00 - 5:00 EST</hours>
          </cntinfo>
        </proccont>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>Class 2, ground LiDAR points are exported from the LAS files into an Arc Geodatabase (GDB) in multipoint format. The 3D breaklines, are imported into the same GDB. An ESRI Terrain is generated from these inputs.</procdesc>
        <srcused>LiDAR Ground Points, Class 2</srcused>
        <procdate>201207</procdate>
        <srcprod>ESRI Terrain</srcprod>
        <proccont>
          <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
              <cntper>Keith Patterson</cntper>
              <cntorg>Dewberry - Geospatial Services Group</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Project Manager</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
              <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
              <address>1000 N. Ashley Drive, Suite 801</address>
              <city>Tampa</city>
              <state>FL</state>
              <postal>33602</postal>
              <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>813.421.8635</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>813.225.1385</cntfax>
            <cntemail>kpatterson@dewberry.com</cntemail>
            <hours>8:00 - 5:00 EST</hours>
          </cntinfo>
        </proccont>
      </procstep>
      <procstep>
        <procdesc>The ESRI Terrain is converted to a raster. The raster was created with a 1 meter cell size. The raster is then split into 1500 x 1500 m tiles</procdesc>
        <srcused>ESRI Terrain</srcused>
        <procdate>201207</procdate>
        <srcprod>Hydro Flattened DEMs</srcprod>
        <proccont>
          <cntinfo>
            <cntperp>
              <cntper>Keith Patterson</cntper>
              <cntorg>Dewberry - Geospatial Services Group</cntorg>
            </cntperp>
            <cntpos>Project Manager</cntpos>
            <cntaddr>
              <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
              <address>1000 N. Ashley Drive, Suite 801</address>
              <city>Tampa</city>
              <state>FL</state>
              <postal>33602</postal>
              <country>USA</country>
            </cntaddr>
            <cntvoice>813.421.8635</cntvoice>
            <cntfax>813.225.1385</cntfax>
            <cntemail>kpatterson@dewberry.com</cntemail>
            <hours>8:00 - 5:00 EST</hours>
          </cntinfo>
        </proccont>
      </procstep>
    </lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <direct>Raster</direct>
    <rastinfo>
      <rasttype>Grid Cell</rasttype>
      <rowcount>1500</rowcount>
      <colcount>1500</colcount>
      <vrtcount>1</vrtcount>
    </rastinfo>
  </spdoinfo>
  <spref>
    <horizsys>
      <planar>
        <mapproj>
          <mapprojn>NAD 1983 UTM Zone 18N</mapprojn>
          <transmer>
            <sfctrmer>0.9996</sfctrmer>
            <longcm>-75.0</longcm>
            <latprjo>0.0</latprjo>
            <feast>500000.0</feast>
            <fnorth>0.0</fnorth>
          </transmer>
        </mapproj>
        <planci>
          <plance>coordinate pair</plance>
          <coordrep>
            <absres>0.000000002220024164500956</absres>
            <ordres>0.000000002220024164500956</ordres>
          </coordrep>
          <plandu>Meter</plandu>
        </planci>
      </planar>
      <geodetic>
        <horizdn>D North American 1983</horizdn>
        <ellips>GRS 1980</ellips>
        <semiaxis>6378137.0</semiaxis>
        <denflat>298.257222101</denflat>
      </geodetic>
    </horizsys>
  </spref>
  <distinfo>
    <distrib>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>USGS</cntorg>
          <cntper>Patrick Emmett</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
          <address>MS 666, 1400 Independence Road</address>
          <city>Rolla</city>
          <state>Missouri</state>
          <postal>65401</postal>
          <country>United States</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>573.308.3587</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>pemmett@usgs.gov</cntemail>
        <hours>8:00 AM - 5:00 PM</hours>
      </cntinfo>
    </distrib>
    <resdesc>Downloadable Data</resdesc>
    <distliab>This data was produced for the USGS according to specific project requirements.  This information is provided "as is".   Further documentation of this data can be obtained by contacting: USGS/NGTOC, 1400 Independence Road, Rolla, MO 65401.  Telephone (573) 308-3587.</distliab>
  </distinfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>201207</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntperp>
          <cntorg>USGS</cntorg>
          <cntper>Patrick Emmett</cntper>
        </cntperp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
          <address>MS 666, 1400 Independence Road</address>
          <city>Rolla</city>
          <state>Missouri</state>
          <postal>65401</postal>
          <country>United States</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>573.308.3587</cntvoice>
        <cntemail>pemmett@usgs.gov</cntemail>
        <hours>8:00 AM - 5:00 PM</hours>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Content Standards for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
    <mettc>local time</mettc>
    <metextns>
      <onlink>http://www.esri.com/metadata/esriprof80.html</onlink>
      <metprof>ESRI Metadata Profile</metprof>
    </metextns>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>